Tufts New England Medical Center Planning Office Records UA014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts New England Medical Center Planning Office Records
1870 -- 1985
1950 -- 1970
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Medical Center
UA014
29.64 Linear Feet 30 boxes, 2 oversized folders.
470 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized in six series: Loose photographs; Correspondence; Audio-visual; Publications; Oversized; and Subject files.
Custodial History
The records of the T-NEMC Planning Office were "divided between the Archives of New England Medical Center, which has approximately 27 feet, and the archives of Tufts University in Medford, which has approximately 20 feet. These are not distinct segments; they are a single unit that has been arbitrarily divided." Along the way the original order of the collection was lost, and many files appear to have been re-foldered and some labeled incorrectly.
The collection at Tufts contains a list of the NEMC portion (UA014.001 11:003), as well as a 1979 letter from Herman H. Field, director of the Planning Office, to the Wessell Archives (currently the Tufts Archives) outlining his ideas for the "Possible Organization of Tufts N.E. Medical Center Planning office Archives." (UA014.001 11:003). Originally, the files appear to have been organized by color, as is apparent by the multi-color labels which still exist on the original folders. The collection contains a copy of the Planning Office's "File Organization Color Guide" and "File Organization Filing Guide" (UA014.001 11:003) which explain the original systems in place. However, the colors have faded and many files were re-foldered prior to the collection arriving at Tufts, therefore the original arrangement could not and was not maintained.
An accurate box list, entitled "15 boxes of files and bound materials" exists which outlines the contents of the 16 boxes which were received by Tufts Archives prior to processing.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes administrative files and records, grant applications and proposals, reports, studies, surveys, architectural plans, contracts, meeting and conference agendas and minutes, correspondence, publications, theses, sound recordings, and visual materials, such as transparencies and photographs, from the Tufts New England Medical Center Planning Office.
Biographical / Historical
The New England Medical Center (NEMC) is the principal teaching hospital for Tuft's School of Medicine and School of Dental Medicine. The Medical Center's chiefs of service are joint appointees with the medical school and most serve as chairs of their respective departments at the medical school. Students take 25% of their required third year clerkships and 50% of their fourth year electives at NEMC.
Recognizing that education and research are essential components to good medical care, the New England Medical Center was established in 1930 through the alliance of the Boston Dispensary, the Boston Floating Hospital for Infants and Children, and the Trustees of Tufts College. The NEMC was established as a non-profit corporation to coordinate the administrative activities of its constituent organizations. In 1946 the Joseph H. Pratt Diagnostic Hospital, an extension of the Boston Dispensary established in 1938, joined NEMC. In 1950, when the Medical School and Dental School relocated to Harrison Avenue, and the NEMC became known as the New England Medical Center Hospital.
The entity was renamed Tufts-New England Medical Center in 1968, and in 1970 the NEMC board met at the Coonamessett Inn in Falmouth, Massachusetts to outline ways the NEMC and Tufts could further coordinate operations. The resulting directives, known as the Coonamessett Statement, indicated that support services and other business functions should be made the responsibility of T-NEMC in each case where it made sense to do so. That same year Tufts President Hallowell and NEMC President Quarles signed an affiliation agreement that codified the T-NEMC as an alliance through which its constituent units would move toward a completely integrated operation. By 1976, T-NEMC controlled health care studies, medical engineering, community health and ambulatory care, employee-student health services, lab animal medicine, some research, off-site medical services, a common utility supply center, architectural services, communications, educational media, parking facilities, property ownership, and public relations. However, by the late 1970s both institutions had experienced a change in leadership, resulting in a change of priorities for each. Interest in integration waned and the cooperation forged in the early 1970s was dismantled.
After a period of tension and competition in the 1980s, Tufts and NEMC drafted a new affiliation agreement in 1991, which remains in effect as of 1999. In 2000, the center was once again named Tufts-New England Medical Center, or T-NEMC.
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research.
Administration and Governance -- Planning, evaluation, policies & procedures; Administration and Governance -- Accreditation; Facilities
- Loose photographs, 1870 -- 1976; 1960 -- 1970; UA014.001; 1.2 Linear Feet; 470 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains images of the South Cove area of Boston before and during construction of the Tufts New England Medical Center.
  Arrangement
  This series has no arrangement.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - New England Medical Center model and poster, 1950; UA014.001.DO.02762; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    Models (representations); Tufts New England Medical Center, records; New England Medical Center
  - Blueprint of medical school layout, 1969; UA014.001.DO.02763; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 39)
    "Real estate consolidated under urban development and Tuft-New England Medical Center site plan, ca. 1969"
    Plan views; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; New England Medical Center
  - Quincy School at 90 Tyler Street, Boston, 1965; UA014.001.DO.02765; Daniels, Robert E. (Box Shared 39)
    Title attached to photo: "Existing 125 year old neighborhood school, now 100% Chinese, first graded school in the United States."
    Buildings; Schools; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Quincy School
  - Model of the Quincy School Complex, 1969; UA014.001.DO.02766; Daniels, Robert E. (Box Shared 39)
    Model of the Quincy School Complex as viewed from the south across the Massachusetts Turnpike.
  - South on Washington Street from Oak Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02768; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    From folder marked "Photos of existing buildings - South Cove area".
    Buildings; Automobiles; Signs; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - South on Tremont Street from Boylston Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02769; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
  - View of Don Bosco Technical High School from the corner of Tremont and Broadway Streets, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02770; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    This image is from a folder marked "Photos of existing buildings - South Cove area".
    Buildings; Schools; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Don Bosco Technical High School
  - View north on Tremont Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02771; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    Buildings; Signs; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Kneeland Street west from Hudson Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02772; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    Buildings; Automobiles; Signs; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View northeast of Tremont Street from the corner of Tremont and Arlington Streets, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02773; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    Views; Buildings; Streets; Bridges (built works); People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View west of Kneeland Street with Tyler Street in the foreground, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02774; Unknown (Box Shared 39)
    Buildings; Automobiles; Signs; People
  - Two unidentified individuals walking towards Ash Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02775; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View south of Tyler Street with Harvard Street in the foreground, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02776; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Metropolitan Building on Tremont Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02777; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View north of Tremont Street from Shawmut Avenue, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02778; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View east of Harvard Street across Tyler Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02779; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View west of Harvard Street from Hudson Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02780; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Automobiles; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View east of Kneeland Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02781; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Signs; Automobiles; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of buildings and a church in the South Cove area, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02782; Keller, Robert J. (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Churches; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of a street and buildings in South Cove area, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02783; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View of a street and buildings in South Cove area, 1945; UA014.001.DO.02784; Keller, Robert J. (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View north of Harrison Avenue from in front of the Boston Dispensary, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02785; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Automobiles; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Boston Dispensary
  - View of the Boston Dispensary in the South Cove area, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02786; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Boston Dispensary
  - View north of Tremont Street with Stuart Street in the foreground, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02787; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View south of Washington Street from Essex Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02788; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
  - View northeast of Tremont Street from Corning Street, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02789; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f2688dd3048e6f71356a330e6e7cb564)
    Buildings; Signs; Automobiles; People; Street railroads; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of a building entrance, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02790; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Buildings; Entrances; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of a parking lot and building, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02791; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Buildings; Signs; Automobiles; People
  - View of an unidentified man walking down an alley in the South Cove area, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02792; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Buildings; Automobiles; People; Alleys; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Boston Dispensary in the South Cove area, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02793; Unknown (Box Shared 40)
  - View of Kneeland Street at Washington Street in the South Cove area, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02794; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Color slides
    Buildings; Signs; People; Street lights; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Partially demolished building belonging to the Tufts New England Medical Center, 1964; UA014.001.DO.02795; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Automobiles; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Tufts New England Medical Center
  - The South Cove area "T", 1971-05; UA014.001.DO.02796; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Subways; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Tai Tung Village sign, 1971-07; UA014.001.DO.02797; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Signs; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Crane at a construction site in the South Cove area, 1971-05; UA014.001.DO.02798; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Building sites; Hoisting machinery; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - South Cove area "T" station, 1971-05; UA014.001.DO.02799; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Automobiles; Subway stations; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - 2 Ash Street, 1968-10; UA014.001.DO.02800; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Subway stations; Subways; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Harvard Street intersection, 1969-11; UA014.001.DO.02801; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Signs; Street lights; People; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of Stuart Street from Washington Street, 1968; UA014.001.DO.02802; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Building sites; Hoisting machinery; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Construction site viewed from Ash and Bennet Streets looking towards Stuart Street, 1970-06; UA014.001.DO.02803; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Building sites; Subway stations; Subways; People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Demolition of a Tufts New England Medical Center building, 1970; UA014.001.DO.02804; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Street lights; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Harvard Street looking towards Stuart Street, 1970; UA014.001.DO.02805; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Hoisting machinery; Snow; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of a subway tunnel and the rear of Washington Street from Ash and Bennet Streets, 1970; UA014.001.DO.02806; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Demolition sites; Subways; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Game of table tennis, 1971-08; UA014.001.DO.02807; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    People; Athletics; Table tennis; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Chinatown residents playing games, 1967; UA014.001.DO.02808; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    People; Games; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Broadway Street between Harrison and Washington Streets, 1962-07; UA014.001.DO.02809; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Signs; Automobiles; Subways; People; Street lights; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Corner of Curve and Broadway Streets, 1962-07; UA014.001.DO.02810; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Bridges (built works); Automobiles; Street lights; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - South Cove area housing, 1962; UA014.001.DO.02811; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Houses; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Tyler Street, 1970-12; UA014.001.DO.02812; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
  - South Cove Park, 1969; UA014.001.DO.02813; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Parks (grounds); Signs; People; Automobiles; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - A martial arts demonstration, 1971; UA014.001.DO.02820; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    People; Oriental hand-to-hand fighting; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Unidentified people standing on a sidewalk in Chinatown, 1971; UA014.001.DO.02821; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    People; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Subway approaching a tunnel in the South Cove area, 1969; UA014.001.DO.02822; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Subways; Snow; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Alley between apartment buildings located in the South Cove area, 1970; UA014.001.DO.02823; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Apartment houses; Alleys; Fences; Clotheslines
  - View of an elevated portion of the "T", 1970; UA014.001.DO.02825; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Automobiles; Subways
  - Drawing of the Old Boston Dispensary, 1880; UA014.001.DO.02826; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; People; Vehicles; Carriages and coaches; Old Boston Dispensary
  - View of Medical Center from the Southeast Expressway. Medical Center expansion is colored, 1970; UA014.001.DO.02827; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Views; Buildings; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; New England Medical Center
  - Chinatown, 1962; UA014.001.DO.02828; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Signs; Automobiles; People; Street lights; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Boston Floating Hospital, 1920; UA014.001.DO.02829; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Hospitals; Ships; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Boston Floating Hospital
  - Hudson Street housing in the South Cove area, 1962-07; UA014.001.DO.02830; Unknown (Box Shared 41)
    Buildings; Houses; Automobiles; Street lights
  - Herbert Gallagher of The Architects Collaborative points out details of the proposed model Hermann H. Field of the Tufts-New England Medical Center Planning Office, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03018; Unknown (Box Shared 34)
    People; Models (representations); Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Field, Hermann; Gallagher, Herbert; New England Medical Center
  - An artist's rendering of a proposed addition to the Tufts-New England Medical Center expansion, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03019; Unknown (Box Shared 34)
    This imagine is a copy of UI03411 (2x2 in. color slide).
    Buildings; Hospitals; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; New England Medical Center
  - A model of an expanded Tufts-New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03020; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
  - Robert W. Meserve (left) and John R. Quarles looking at model of construction and expansion program at Tufts-New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03021; Unknown (Box Shared 34)
    Title attached to photo: "Looking at model of $72.5 million construction and expansion program at Tufts-New England Medical Center are Robert W. Meserve, Chairman of the Board of Trustees for Tufts University (left) and John R. Quarles, President of the Board of Governors for the New England Medical Center Hospitals."
    People; Models (representations); Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Meserve, Robert W.; Quarles, John R.; New England Medical Center
  - 95 acre South Cove Renewal Area and 15 acre Medical Center Development Plan, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03022; Unknown (Box Shared 34)
    Views; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Tufts New England Medical Center
  - Harvard Street ambulance entrance, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03023; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Entrances; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Illustrative site plan for the regional core, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03024; Boston Redevelopment Authority (Box Shared 34)
  - Site plan showing road routes to and from the New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03025; Unknown (Box Shared 34)
  - Artist's rendering of a proposed addition to the Tufts-New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03026; Unknown (Box Shared 34)
  - Building in the South Cove area, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03027; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Buildings; Automobiles
  - View of the Music Hall Theater from Tremont Street, 1967-12; UA014.001.DO.03028; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Buildings; Theaters; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Music Hall Theater
  - A modular growth diagram of the Tufts-New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03029; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
    Title attached to photo: "Theoretical modular growth diagram across Washington Street & above pedestrian circulation system. The Architects Collaborative."
  - Site plan showing existing New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03030; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Model of the Tufts-New England Medical Center, Stage I, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03031; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Model of the Tufts-New England Medical Center, Stage I and II, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03032; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Plan showing the positioning of the New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03033; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 33)
    Title attached to photo: "Medical Center at hinge point in Boston commercial spine, with the new Government Center to the north and the Prudential Center to the west."
  - View of buildings in the South Cove area, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03034; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Buildings; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - Model of the Quincy School Complex, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03035; Daniels, Robert E. (Box Shared 34)
    Title attached to photo: "Model of the Quincy School Complex as viewed from the northwest."
  - Quincy School Complex, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03036; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Master plan for the Tufts-New England Medical Center, Stage 1, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03037; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Master plan for the Tufts-New England Medical Center, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03038; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Master plan for the Tufts-New England Medical Center, Stage 2, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03039; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box Shared 34)
  - Master plan for the Tufts-New England Medical Center, Priority staging, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03040; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box data_value_missing_f192f5c8820b07dbf78c0820404a09b6)
  - Master plan for the Tufts-New England Medical Center, Pedestrian Level I, 1969; UA014.001.DO.03041; The Architects Collaborative, INC. (Box data_value_missing_f192f5c8820b07dbf78c0820404a09b6)
  - Two doors leading into a building, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03042; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Building most likely to be located on Harvard St. or Monsignor Shea Rd.
    Doors; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of buildings and sidewalks along Harvard Street or Monsignor Shea Road, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03043; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Note with photo places the location at Harvard St. or Monsignor Shea Rd.
  - Truck parked in front of the Ziskind Research Laboratories located on Harvard Street or Monsignor Shea Road, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03044; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Buildings; Laboratories; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; Ziskind Research Laboratories
  - Entrance to the rectory of St. James's Church, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03045; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Rectory possibly located on Harvard St. or Monsignor Shea Rd.
    Buildings; Churches; Entrances; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; St. James' Church
  - Windows and entrance to the rectory of St. James' Church, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03046; Unknown (Box Shared 33)
    Buildings; Churches; Entrances; Doors; Windows; Tufts New England Medical Center, records; St. James' Church
  - Street corner and surrounding buildings in the South Cove area, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03047; Harvey, Robert D. (Box data_value_missing_f192f5c8820b07dbf78c0820404a09b6)
    Buildings; Theaters; Signs; Automobiles; People
  - Music Hall Theater located on the corner of Hollis and Tremont Streets., 1967; UA014.001.DO.03048; Harvey, Robert D. (Box data_value_missing_f192f5c8820b07dbf78c0820404a09b6)
    Buildings; Theaters; Signs; Automobiles; People; Music Hall Theater
  - View from above of the South Cove area, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03049; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f192f5c8820b07dbf78c0820404a09b6)
    Views; Buildings; Tufts New England Medical Center, records
  - View of the Music Hall Theater from Dillaway Street, 1967; UA014.001.DO.03050; Unknown (Box data_value_missing_f192f5c8820b07dbf78c0820404a09b6)
    Consists of 4 separate photos taped together.